McKelvey, Jean T. Additional Papers /4180
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Jean T. McKelvey Additional Papers
1978-1996
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
McKelvey, Jean T.
/4180
5 cubic feet
5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
8036539
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, December 17, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 03, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Jean McKelvey (February 9, 1908 January 5, 1998) was one of the founding faculty at the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1946, the first female member of the National Academy of Arbitrators (NAA) in 1947, the NAA's first female president in 1970, and an accomplished author of many works on arbitration and other labor topics. The first fully endowed chair at the ILR School was named the Jean McKelvey-Alice Grant Professorship of Labor-Management Relations.
A graduate of Wellesley College (AB '29, MA '31) and Radcliffe College (PhD '33), McKelvey taught at Sarah Lawrence College from 1932 to 1945. She joined the newly-formed New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations in 1946 as the school's first professor, reaching the rank of full professor in 1951. She became Professor Emerita in 1976. In addition to developing the ILR School's fields of study with Maurice Neufeld, teaching at the ILR School, and conducting scholarly research, McKelvey served on the Region II National War Labor Board (1944-1945), New York State Board of Mediation (1955-1966), the Federal Services Impasses Panel (1979-1990), and other boards and panels.
Among her many honors and awards were the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service's Special Award for Distinguished Service in Labor Management Relations (1973), Arbitrator of the Year Award from the American Arbitration Association (1983), and Distinguished Services Awards from Wellesley College (1975), the Society of Professionals in Dispute Resolution (1989), and the Society of Federal Labor Relations Professionals (1990).
See the Cornell University Faculty Memorial Statement for Professor Jean McKelvey: http://hdl.handle.net/1813/18133
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3001: Jean T. McKelvey Papers
McKelvey, Jean T.(Jean Trepp), 1908-1998; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
8036539
- Ser II B., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ser. II B. Alice Grant (Folder 1 of 2), 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ser II B. Alice Grant (Folder 2 of 2), 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ser II B (Folder 1 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ser II B. (Folder 2 of 2), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Morton Bahr, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ser. II B (Labor Studies Program 1980-83), 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ser. II B., 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ser. II. B. Grant, Alice Memorial Fund, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes memorials, tributes, financial data, corresp
- Ser II. A. Dean Lipsky 987-95, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ser. II A. Financial Expense Accounts, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ser II A. ILR School Appointments, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ser II A. Ext. Div. - Lois Gray, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Ser II. A Ext Div. Ron Seber, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Xerox Grad Courses, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Buffalo Grad. Progress, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Grad Programs 90-91, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Grad Couses 91-92 Off Campus, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Grad Courses92-93, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Off Campus Grad Courses 91-92 Albany Central Districts, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ser. II, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Picture of Groat '85 Award Luncheon
- 50th Anniv Volume Editor Pubs of Ser. II A ??, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ser. II A. Ext. Committee Questionnaire, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Wallen Ford Committee Ser. II B. "ILR Comm. Files", 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Ford Foundation Wallen Interns, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Ser. II B Wallen Fund 1982-83, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ser. II B. Wallen Fund 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ser. II B Wallen Fund 1981, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Ser II B. Wallen Fund 1980, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Ser II B. Wallen Fund 1979, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Ser. II B. Wallen Fund 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Ser. II B. Wallen Minutes 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Ser. II B. Wallen Fund 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Cornell Budget Figures on Grant of Wallen Funds, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Ser. II B. Wallen Fund 1987-88, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Labor Management Issues in the 90's Ser II C., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ser II C. Federal L. Rel 2nd An. Symposium Ithaca 9/11 & 12/85, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Ser II C. DFR Roch Conf 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Ser II C., 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ser II C. Lora Conference 1980, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- J. McKelacy- Cornell University The New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Arbitrator Training- Minorities, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Arbitration Program Inquiries, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Arb. Conference Rochester 5/7/80, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Arb. Conference Advocates- Roch 11/79, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- A Conference on Dispute Resolution in the Federal Sector, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Sen II C. Women Arb, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- WADP Records & Addresses, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Reunion 1981 WADP, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Women Arbitrators Graduation, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Womens Arbitrators Development Program, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Women Arbitrators Reunion -D.C., 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Some photographs
- Barker, Christine M., 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Berger, Robin M., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Bradley, Belen Acosta, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Bussey, Ellen M., 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Buzbee, Ellen Wade, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Cole, Sheila, 1979-1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Dyke, Annmarie K., 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Freedman, Adeline, 1979-1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Gillespie, Sally C., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Gilman, Tamara Lyons, 1979-1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Goldy, Jill A. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Gwiazda, Suzanne B., 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Johnson, Gloria, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Joseph, Camelia, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Mills, Miriam K., 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Plitt, Jane R., 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Rappaport, Lois A., 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Richman, Terry M., 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Schneider, Randy Jeanne, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Siber-Weinstock, Bonnie, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Sipser, Margaret Ann, 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Smith, Anna D., 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Wittenberg, Carol A., 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Ser II C AIDS & Drug Testing in the Workplace (Folder 1 of 4), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Ser II C AIDS & Drug Testing in the Workplace (Folder 2 of 4), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Ser II C AIDS & Drug Testing in the Workplace (Folder 3 of 4), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Ser II C AIDS & Drug Testing in the Workplace (Folder 4 of 4), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Ser III Prof. Org's AAA Advisory Committee, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Supreme Ct. Decisions, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Ser VI A) Rights of Ind. EES Dismissal at Will, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Ser VI A) Rights of Ind. EES Dismissal at Will, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Ser VI A Lab-mgmt Corporation, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Ser VI A Judicial Review, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Ser VI A) Dismissal At Will, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Ser VI A Conference Ideas, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Ser VI A Conference Programs 1982, 1982-1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)